I grew up
كبِرتُ
diagnosed as phobically shy,
وتم تشخيصي كشخص خجول نتيجة الخوف
I was a stutterer.
كنت أتلعثم في الكلام
Do you dare raise your hand?
هل تتجرءون على رفع ايديكم؟
because when we are treated that way,
لأننا عندما نُعامل بهذه الطريقة،
we feel invisible sometimes,
نشعر بأننا غير مرئيون بعض الأحيان
or talked around and at.
أو لا يُتَحدّث الينا بإهتمام.
And as I started to look at people,
بدات أنظر إلى الناس
which is mostly all I did,
وهذا تقريباً كل ما أقوم به،
I noticed that some people
لاحظتُ أن بعض الناس
really wanted attention and recognition.
يحتاجون حقا للإنتباه والإعتراف بوجودهم
Remember, I was young then.
تذكروا، كنت صغيرة عندئذٍ
So what did they do?
ماذا عملوا؟
What we still do perhaps too often.
ما الذي نزال نفعله عادةً
We talk about ourselves.
أننا نتحدث عن أنفسنا
And yet there are other people I observed
ولكن لاحظت أن هناك أُناس
who had what I called a mutuality mindset.
لديهم ما أدعوه بـ"الفكر المتبادل"
In each situation, they found a way to talk about us
في كل ظرف، يجدون طريقة للتحدُث عنا
and create that "us" idea.
وخلق فكرة "نحن"
So my idea to reimagine the world
لذلك، فكرتي لتخيل العالم بطريق أخرى
greater opportunity-makers with and for others.
صُنّاع فُرص مع ومن أجل الآخرين
or call for action for us now
أو دعوة للتغير لنا الآن
who use best talents together more often
يستخدمُون أفضل مواهِبهُم غالباً
for the greater good
من أجل خيرٍ أكبر
and accomplish things we couldn't have done on our own.
ويُنجِزون أشياء لا نستطيع انجازها بانفُسِنا
And I want to talk to you about that,
أريد ان أحدِثكم عن ذلك،
because even more than giving,
لأنه ماهو حتى أكثر من العطاء،
is the capacity for us to do something smarter
هو القدرة التي تجعلنا نعمل شيء أكثر ذكاءً
together for the greater good
مع بعضنا لخيرٍ أكبر
that lifts us both up
هذا يرفعنا ويفيدنا جميعاً
and that can scale.
وهذا يمكن أن يزداد
That's why I'm sitting here.
لهذا السبب أنا موجودة هنا،
But I also want to point something else out:
ولكن أريد أن اُشير لشيء ما
is better than anybody else at something.
يتفوّق على الآخر في شيء ما
That disproves that popular notion
وهذا يُناقض النظرية المشهورة
that if you're the smartest person in the room,
أذا أنت الشخص الاكثر ذكاءً في الغرفة،
you're in the wrong room.
فأنت في المكان الخطأ
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So let me tell you about
لذلك دعُني اُخبركم عن
a Hollywood party I went to a couple years back,
حفلة هوليود التي ذهبت اليها منذ سنتين،
and I met this up-and-coming actress,
وقابلت هذه الممثلة الصاعدة
and we were soon talking about something
وتحدثنا عن بعض الاشياء
that we both felt passionately about: public art.
التي نشعر كلانا بالشغف نحوها "الفن العام"
And she had the fervent belief
كان عندها اعتقاد مُتقد أن
that every new building in Los Angeles
كل مبنى في لوس انجلوس
should have public art in it.
يجب أن يحتوي على نوع من الفن.
She wanted a regulation for it,
أرادت تعميم من أجل ذلك
and she fervently started —
وبالفعل بدأت بكل حماس
who is here from Chicago? —
من هنا من شيكاغو؟
she fervently started talking about
بدأت بحماس تتحدث عن
these bean-shaped reflective sculptures
تلك المنحوته على شكل اللوبيا ذات المرايا المقعرة و المحدبّة
in Millennium Park,
في "ميلنيوم بارك"
and people would walk up to it
التي يذهب الناس لرؤيتها
and they'd smile in the reflection of it,
ويبتسمون في انعكاسها
and they'd pose and they'd vamp
ويتوقفون لأخذ صورة بجانبها
and they'd take selfies together,
وياخذون صورة لأنفسهم معاً "سيلفي"
and they'd laugh.
ويضحكون.
And as she was talking, a thought came to my mind.
وبينما كانت تتحدث، خطرت لي فكرة
I said, "I know someone you ought to meet.
قلت لها "اعرف شخصاً ينبغي أن تقابليه"
He's getting out of San Quentin in a couple of weeks" —
سيأتي من "سان كونتين" خلال اسبوعين
(Laughter) —
(ضحك)
"and he shares your fervent desire
يشاركًكِ هذه الرغبة المتقدة
that art should engage and enable people to connect."
أن الفن يجب أن يجذب الناس ويمكنهم من التواصل
He spent five years in solitary,
لقد أمضى خمسة اعوام في عزلة
and I met him because I gave a speech at San Quentin,
وقابلته لأني القيت خطاباً في "سان كونتين"
and he's articulate
وكان لبق
and he's rather easy on the eyes because he's buff.
ومن السهل ملاحظته لأنه ذو بنية قوية
He had workout regime he did every day.
كان يمارس تمارين الحمية الغذائية كل يوم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I think she was following me at that point.
اعتقد أنها كانت تتابعني في هذه النقطة
I said, "He'd be an unexpected ally."
قلت لها "سيكون حليف غير متوقع"
And not just that. There's James. He's an architect
وليس ذلك فقط ، هنالك "جيمس" هو مهندس معماري
and he's a professor, and he loves place-making,
وهو أيضاً بروفسور ويحب بناء المنحوتات الفنية في الأماكن العامة
and place-making is when you have
والتي يمكن أن تجدها
those mini-plazas and those urban walkways
في مراكز التسوق الصغيرة وعلى طرقات المدنية
and where they're dotted with art,
المزخرفة بالفن
where people draw and come up and talk sometimes.
حيث يرسم الناس ويأتون ليتحدثوا بعض الأحيان،
I think they'd make good allies.
أعتقد أنهم سيكونوا حلفاء جيدون
And indeed they were.
وبالفعل، كانوا كذلك
They met together. They prepared.
لقد تقابلوا وقاموا بالتحضير،
They spoke in front of the Los Angeles City Council.
تحدثوا امام مجلس مدينة "لوس انجلوس"
And the council members not only passed the regulation,
واعضاء المجلس لم يصدروا القانون فحسب،
half of them came down and asked to pose with them afterwards.
يل أن نصفهم نزلوا وطلبوا ان يقفوا معهم، بعد الجلسة.
They were startling, compelling and credible.
كانوا مذهلين وجبارين وجديرون بالثقة
You can't buy that.
لن تستطيعوا تصديق ذلك.
What I'm asking you to consider
ما اطلبه منكم ان تأخذوه بعين الأعتبار هو
is what kind of opportunity- makers we might become,
أي نوع من صُناع الفُرص قد نكون،
because more than wealth
لأن ماهو أكثر من الثروة
or fancy titles
والالقاب الفاخرة
around each other's better side and bring it out.
حول الجانب الجيد من بعضنا واظهاره
And I'm not saying this is easy,
وانا لا اقول أن هذا بالأمر السهل،
and I'm sure many of you have made the wrong moves too
وأنا متأكدة أن العديد منكم قد قاموا بالخطوة الخاطئة
but what I want to suggest is,
ولكن ما أريد أن اقترحه هو
this is an opportunity.
أن هذه فرصة
I started thinking about it
بداتُ اُفكر بها
way back when I was a Wall Street Journal reporter
منذ وقت طويل عندما كنت مراسلة صحفية في "وول ستريت"
and I was in Europe and I was supposed to cover trends
وكنت حينها في اوروبا وكان يجب عليّ تغطية التطورات
and trends that transcended business
وتوجهات إدارة الاعمال
or politics or lifestyle.
أو السياسة أو اساليب الحياة
So I had to have contacts
لذلك، توجب عليّ ان يكون لدي اتصالات
in different worlds very different than mine,
بعالم مختلف جداً عن عالمي،
because otherwise you couldn't spot the trends.
وإلا ما استطعتُ تغطية التوجُهات المختلفة
And third, I had to write the story
وثالثاً، كان يتوجّبُ عليّ أن اكتب قصة
in a way stepping into the reader's shoes,
بطريقة تجعلني اراها من وجة نظر القُرّاء
so they could see how these trends could affect their lives.
لكي يستطيعوا أن يروا كيف لهذه التوجهات أن تؤثر بحياتهم
That's what opportunity-makers do.
هذا ما يفعله صُناع الفُرص
And here's a strange thing:
وها هُنا شيء غريب:
Unlike an increasing number of Americans
بعكس عدد الأمريكان المتزايد
who are working and living and playing with people
الذين يعملون ويعيشون ويلعبون مع اُناس
who think exactly like them
يفكرون مثلهم بالضبط
because we then become more rigid and extreme,
لاننا نصبح عندها اكثر جمود وتطرف
opportunity-makers are actively seeking situations
صُناع الفرص يبحثون بنشاط عن ظروف تجمعهم
and they're building relationships,
ويبنون معهم علاقات
and because they do that,
ولأنهم يفعلون ذلك،
they have trusted relationships
لديهم علاقات موثوقة
where they can bring the right team in
حيث يستطيعون أن يُحضروا الفريق الصحيح
and recruit them to solve a problem better and faster
وتدريبهم على حل المشاكل بطريقة افضل وأسرع
and seize more opportunities.
ويمسكون بفرص أكثر
They're not affronted by differences,
ليسوا مُهانون بسب الاختلافات
they're fascinated by them,
ولكن معجبون بها
and that is a huge shift in mindset,
وهذا تغّيرٌ كبير في الفكر
and once you feel it, you want it to happen a lot more.
وعندما تشعر به، تريده أن يحدث أكثر
This world is calling out for us to have a collective mindset,
هذا العالم يدعونا أن نمتلك فِكر جماعي
and I believe in doing that.
وأنا اؤمن بالقيام بذلك
It's especially important now.
وهو مهم خصوصا في الوقت الراهن
Why is it important now?
لماذا هو ذلك مهم الآن؟
Because things can be devised like drones
لأن الاشياء يمكن أن تُبتكر كالطائرات بلا طيار
and drugs and data collection,
والمخدرات وجمع المعلومات
and they can be devised by more people
ومن الممكن أن تُبتكر من قِبل العديد من الناس
and cheaper ways for beneficial purposes
بطرق اقل تكلفة ومن أجل أهداف مفيدة
and then, as we know from the news every day,
وكما نعرف من الأخبار كل يوم
they can be used for dangerous ones.
من الممكن أن تُستخدم في اشياء خطيرة
It calls on us, each of us,
هذا يستدعينا جميعا
to a higher calling.
لرفع مناشادتنا
But here's the icing on the cake:
ولكن المشكلة
It's not just the first opportunity
ليست فقط الفرصة الأولى
that you do with somebody else
التي تخلُقها لشخص
that's probably your greatest,
قد تكون أعظم ما تقدمة
as an institution or an individual.
كافرد أو مؤسسة
It's after you've had that experience
انها بعد ان تكتسب الخبرة
and you trust each other.
وتثقوا ببعضكم البعض
It's the unexpected things
إنها الأشياء الغير متوقعة
that you devise later on
التي تبتكرها لاحقاً
you never could have predicted.
ولم تكن لتتوقعها ابدًا
For example, Marty is the husband of that actress I mentioned,
على سبيل المثال، "مارتي" زوج الممثلة التي حثتكم عنها
and he watched them when they were practicing,
شاهدهم عندما كانوا يتدربون
and he was soon talking to Wally,
وبعدها تحدث مع "والي"
my friend the ex-con,
صديقي الذي كان حبيس عزلته
about that exercise regime.
عن تمارين الحمية الغذائية
And he thought,
واعتقد هو
I have a set of racquetball courts.
"أن لدي نادي لكرة المضرب
That guy could teach it.
ذلك الرجل يستطيع تعليمها
A lot of people who work there are members at my courts.
العديد من الناس الذين يعملون هناك هم اعضاء في ناديّ
They could practice in their hotel room,
يستطيعون التدرب في غرفهم في الفندق
no equipment provided.
وبدون معدّات
That's how Wally got hired.
لذلك حصل "والي" على الشغل
Not only that, years later
وليس ذلك فحسب، بعد عام
he was also teaching racquetball.
لقد كان يدرّب كرة المضرب
he was teaching the racquetball teachers.
لقد كان يدرّب المدرّبين كرة المضرب
you're accustomed to serendipitous
تصبح متعود على اكتشاف
things happening into the future,
اشياء تحدث في المستقبل
and I think that's what we're looking at.
وهذا ما ننظر اليه في إعتقادي
We open ourselves up to those opportunities,
ننفتح على تلك الفرص
and in this room are key players in technology,
وفي هذه الغرفة هنالك أشخاص فعالين في مجال التكنلوجيا
key players who are uniquely positioned to do this,
مفاتيح تشغيل موضوعة خصيصا لتقوم بذلك
to scale systems and projects together.
لتطوير العمل والمشاريع معًا
So here's what I'm calling for you to do.
لذلك، هذا ما ادعوكم لتفعلوه
Remember the three traits of opportunity-makers.
تذكروا ثلاث صفات لصُناع الفُرص
Opportunity-makers keep honing their top strength
صناع الفرص: يواصلون صقل قواهم
They get involved in different worlds than their worlds
يتداخلون في عوالم غير عالمهم
so they're trusted and they can see those patterns,
لذلك هم جديرون بالثقة ويستطيعون معرفة تلك التطورات
and they communicate to connect
يتواصلون ليصلوا
around sweet spots of shared interest.
الى مناطق ملهمة من الاهتمامات المشتركة
So what I'm asking you is,
لذلك، ما اطلبه منكم هو أن
the world is hungry.
العالم جائع
I truly believe, in my firsthand experience,
أؤمن بالتجربة الأولى
the world is hungry for us
العالم يحتاجنا
to unite together as opportunity-makers
لنتوحد جميعًا كصنّاع للفُرص
and to emulate those behaviors
ولكي نضاهي تلك التصرفات
as so many of you already do —
التي فعلها أشخاص مثلكم من قبل
I know that firsthand —
اعرف ان التجربة الأولى
and to reimagine a world
ولكي نتخيل العالم بطريقة اخرى
where we use our best talents together
حيث نستخدم افضل مواهبنا معا
more often to accomplish greater things together
في الغالب لكي ننجز اشياء اعظم معاً
than we could on our own.
من ما قد ننجزه بمفردنا
Just remember,
فقط تذكروا
as Dave Liniger once said,
كما قال مرّه "ديف لينيجر"
"You can't succeed
"لا تستطيع النجاح
coming to the potluck with only a fork."
عند حضور حفلة مليئة بالطعام و تاتي بشوكة فقط
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلاً
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرًا (تصفيق)